A Guide to the Papers of the Ellison Family 1838-1940
Roanoke Public Libraries
Roanoke Public Libraries
A Guide to the Papers of the Ellison Family
Roanoke Public Libraries
2013.8.26
7 record storage boxes
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Beirne Ellison
Biographical Information
Mr. Beirne Ellison was born August 29, 1870 in the community of Forest Hills in Summers County, West Virginia. Ellison worked a teacher in the 1890s. He was often referred to as Professor Ellison. In 1900 he served as the principal of the Pembroke Grammar School in Kimbalton, Virginia. When Ellison was not teaching during the summers, he was employed in resort hotels. He managed the Mountain Lake Hotel in Giles County, Virginia for nearly 20 years. For a short while, Ellison also managed the Blue Ridge Springs Hotel in Botetourt County, Virginia. Ellison was offered a position by Union Mutual Life Insurance Company in Richmond, Virginia in 1909, but only relocated to Roanoke, Virginia in 1920, where he was the district agent for Union Mutual Life Insurance Co. Ellison passed away at the age of 83 on February 27, 1954. Charles L. Ellison and Leona B. Ellison (born Hobbs) were the parents of Beirne Ellison, as well as the parents of Beirne’s siblings, sister Cora, and brothers Orley, Earl, Webb (Webbie), and Ira Ellison. Beirne Ellison was first married to Gracie (or Grace) Ellison, who died in September 1908. Beirne Ellison married his second wife Nannie (or Nancy, born Nannie M. Givens) Ellison in September 1910. Beirne had an Aunt Blane (also Blaine), but the exact family relationship was not determined. Beirne Ellison’s father Charles Ellison was a teacher, who acted as an attorney and served as the county superintendent of schools in 1875. Charles Ellison was designated as the administrator of the estate of Jordan Lively, who was a property owner and whiskey distiller. Beirne Ellison’s mother Leona Ellison, who died in 1894, had three sisters, Jane, Lizzie and Belle, and two brothers, William and Benton Hobbs. Beirne’s wife Nannie Ellison’s mother was named Mertie A. (or Martha) Slusser (or Sluser or Schusser). Apparently Beirne Ellison had four children, a son Marcus (or Mark) Ellison, and three daughters, Mary and Martha Ellison, twins, and Nancy Ellison. Marcus Ellison married De Lila Hayes in 1926.
Scope and Content
This collection is arranged into four main series, and seven subseries, in seven record storage boxes for a total of 10.25 linear feet. The first series is documents and records, which includes official records, lists, receipts, summons, deeds, wills, certificates, financial documents, bank deposits, cancelled checks, and tax statements. The second series is miscellaneous manuscripts, such as notebooks, poems and other non-correspondence of a non-official nature. The third series is published and printed materials. The fourth series is Ellison family correspondence and other correspondence, which is further divided into subseries for the correspondence of Beirne Ellison’s parents Charles L. and Leona B. Ellison, for Beirne Ellison himself, with separate subseries for personal and for business and professional correspondence, for the correspondence of his wives Gracie and Nannie, and finally for the miscellaneous correspondence of other relatives and associates. Apparently Beirne Ellison compiled or retained this collection himself, a collection which includes correspondence, cards, and miscellaneous documents from his family and friends and family associates. The bulk of the materials in the collection were gathered from the 1880s to the early1900s. A few of the documents go back to the ante-bellum period of the nineteenth century, one dated as early as 1838. Among the documents and records are various lists and certificates, including articles of agreement for teaching, teachers’ certificates, church subscriptions, school term and monthly reports, and a wedding invitation for the marriage of Nannie Givens and Beirne Ellison on September 1, 1910. Other documents in the collection are receipts, bank statements, cancelled checks, petitions, articles of financial agreement and copies of deeds, including a deed from Mary F. Huffman to C. A. Sanders. Also among the documents and records are bills of lading and shipping orders, payment agreement notes, a lottery list, a lumber price list, and a railway schedule and train order. There is a menu from the Mountain Lake Hotel, tailor’s measurements for Floyd Snidow, school grades, reports and surveys, various summonses, and a packet of C.O.D. orders for Beirne Ellison. One ante-bellum tax receipt lists the tax paid on a slave. Charles Ellison, Beirne’s father, was a man of substance in West Virginia and Virginia. He was involved in many 19th century business deals and acted as the administrator of the estate of Jordan Lively, who was a property owner and whiskey distiller, whose last will and testament is among the documents. There is also a copy of the will of Samuel Huffman. Many of Charles Ellison’s accounts and business and tax records are included in this collection, as are records from his associates, and some of his correspondence. Manuscripts are varied and include ledger books, notebooks, notes, marginalia, school papers, tests and assignments, poems, and other writings. Many of the notebooks include numerous inserts of various sorts, but have not been disturbed and were left as discovered. Non-official documents and non-correspondence were all included in this category. Publications and printed materials include a large run of church bulletins from 1932 to 1940, the bulk of which are from 1932 to 1938. There are several complete and incomplete books. School grammars, textbooks and atlases are among the publications in the collection. There are brochures, including promotional literature on Mountain Lake and Mountain Lake Hotel, booklets, political flyers, catalogs, a miniature almanac, and a cookbook. Advertising is well represented, both as contents of letters (that is as “junk mail” and enclosures) in the correspondence series, and separate as printed matter in the published and printed materials series. Some of the advertising and promotional literature relates to publications of interest to teachers and educators, and other advertising is aimed at the business of hotel management, farming, or property management in general. Beirne Ellison kept his father Charles Ellison’s personal, professional and business correspondence, which extends from about the end of the civil war until the 1880’s. Charles Ellison’s correspondents included W.W. Adams, J.H. Alderson, F.B. Baber, W.W. Baker, R.G. Ballinger, C.E. Black, Richard Burke, John Casden, Jonathan M. Davis, J.W. Davis, R.L. Deeds, H.M. Dickinson, E.G. Duncan, E.L. Dunn, D.C. Gallaher, William W. Johnson, R.B. Lively, J.D. Logan, R.M. McClelland, John C. McNeer, C.L. and W.W. Rance, William M. Reynolds, Fleming Sanders, J.S. Schumate, A.G. Tabbetts, and C.L. Thompson. Leona Ellison, Beirne Ellison’s mother, maintained an extensive correspondence with relatives, friends, and various associates. She wrote many letters to and received many letters from her brothers Benton Hobbs and William Hobbs, and her sisters Lizzie and Jane. Leona also received numerous missives from Isaac M. Brogles, J.L. Broyles, Mary Crawford, E.L. Dunn (a cousin), Harriet D. Ellison, J.W. Francis, L.P. Hobbs (a nephew), Martha Johnston, A.L. Keadle (an uncle), J.D. Logan, Gracie Lowe (a cousin), Joshua Lowe, J.P. McNutt, E.H. Peck, Horace G. Peck (a nephew), A.J. Skaggs (a dentist), J.D. Thrasher (a physician), John Wanamaker, S. W. Willey, and Jennie Wilson. Beirne Ellison’s earliest surviving letters were written to his mother and are located with the subseries for her correspondence. His personal correspondence begins with letters from the late nineteenth century and continues into the 1930s. Among his family and other associated correspondents are C.L. and Anna E. Boone, E.P. Buchanan, W.H. Buchanan, Julia W. Bullard, Blanche Carroll, Charles Carroll, Nancy A. Dun, Lora Epling, Clarence Fisher, J.H. Gillispie, Sam Gillispie, Emma B. Hale, Hugh Hodge Hill, J.B. Hobbs (Belle’s husband), W.H. Jones, L.D. Keadle, C.L. King, Mrs. E.L. Landrum, Fay Martin, Julia F. May, Fannie A. McLaurey, C.E. Miller, F.C. Nunemacher, C.A. Peck, C.J. Peck, Duke Putney, Eva R. Robinson, Joseph and Mrs. J. Robinson, L.D. Shumate, George L. Smith, Floyd E. Snidow, Frank M. Snidow, Frank P. Snidow, L. B. Snidow, Ethel Snidow (Mrs. L.B. Snidow), Florence W. Thompson, W.B. Thompson, Florence Wells, Nannie S. White, C.A. Worley, Harvey B. Worley, and Mrs. L. Young. There are times when Beirne Ellison’s personal and business or professional letters overlap, so there is not always a clear distinction between these series. Beirne Ellison included business and professional matters in some personal correspondence, and vice versa. Beirne Ellison collected his business and professional correspondence as a teacher, hotel manager and property owner. Among these letters is extensive correspondence about Mountain Lake Hotel with H.E. Dorland (circa 1899-1912), T. Gilbert Porterfield (circa 1900-1909) and others. Other business correspondents include J.D. Bolton, Walter H. Boude, Daisie Buchanan, G.L. and Mrs. G.L. Collins, J.E. Coalter, Lyman Denison, J.E. Dunklee, E.L. Dunn, Charles E. Eckerle, W.J. Finley, Frederic J. Haskin, Mrs. J.C. Heaberlin, Belle G. Hobbs (his aunt), S.F. Humphreys, A.P. Huffman, D.P. Hylton, B.F. Johnson, Nannie Keister, G. L. Kinsley, C.W. Lowe, Mrs. C.W. Lowe, M.E.C. Merriman, C. H. Pack, G.J. Porterfield, W.S. Rogers, L. B. Rowan, M.J. Sanders, M.A. Smythe, John Stickler, Bettie St. Clair, Paul S. Stonesifer, J. H. Walken, Charles Wilkerson, and J. W. Younger. Gracie Ellison’s collected correspondence is mostly addressed to her husband Beirne and spans the period from 1899 to 1902. Nannie Ellison’s correspondence goes back to her life before marrying Beirne Ellison. She has an extensive correspondence with her mother Mertie A. Slusser and other relatives and friends. Her correspondents include an old boyfriend, William J. (Willie) Shelburne, as well as others such as J.A. Campbell, Cora Harper, Lelia Hunter, Lotta McPherson, Hester Price, Mattie Pearle Shelburne, and Clara Warner. Her letters also include correspondence with her husband Beirne and their daughters Mary and Martha. The miscellaneous correspondence includes general mailings to Mountain Lake Hotel as well as correspondence to and from relatives and associates such as Martha Ellison (daughter of Beirne), Webb Ellison (brother of Beirne), Haven Hoge, Jordan Lively, Calvin Moss, Fleming Sanders, and Joseph Patton. Some of the other names that appear among the materials as subjects and correspondents, relatives, friends and associates include: F.E. Atkins, W.H. Ballard, W.S. Beasley, Phebe S. Bell, Lila Bridges, Phil F. Brown, Lacy Crawford, D. L. Duncan, P.B. Durham, J.B. Elkins, J. Taylor Ellyson, G.C. Foster, S.M. Goldsmith, Edward S. Green, Wallace G. Hale, H.H. Hawkins, W.C. Henderson, William Hinchman, G. Hinton, Samuel Hinton, Nancy Hitchens, S.P. Hobbs, Mrs. Ray H. Jester, James Jowett, Ruth Jowett, Mary D. Long, Fleming Lowe, Joshua Lowe, L.C. Lucas, John Lynn, Helen Mason, J.P. McNutt, Thomas Miller, Horace G. Peck, Alice Lemon Price, G.B. Price, C. H. Pritchard, Louise M. Schmidt, Lilia Smith, L.W. Snidow, Alex Turnstall, and Jennie Wilson. There was no order to the materials, as they were received. All of the items in the collection were individually arranged chronologically, from 1938 to 1940. Letters in envelopes were left folded in the envelopes. Letters without envelopes were flattened. Each item was sorted into categories based on the following schema:
Arrangement
The documents are arranged by series and further arranged chronologically within the series. There was no original order to the documents. They were sorted first chronologically, and then arranged by logical series according to types of materials. The arrangement follows the following order: Documents and Records; Manuscripts; Publications and Printed Materials; Charles L. Ellison Correspondence; Leona B. Ellison Correspondence; Beirne Ellison Personal Correspondence; Beirne Ellison Business and Professional Correspondence; Gracie Ellison Correspondence; Nannie Ellison Correspondence; and Miscellaneous Correspondence.
Contents List
- Documents and Records, 1843-1928 (Box 1)
  - James and Ruth Jowett Indenture, Estate of Samuel Hinton 1843 (Folder 1)
  - Hinchman and Hinton Deed 1849 (Folder 2)
  - Jordan Lively, Indenture 1851 (Folder 3)
  - Jordan Lively Deeds 1852-1854 (Folder 4)
  - Jordan Lively Deed 1856 (Folder 5)
  - Charles Ellison, Receipt and Deed 1860-1861 (Folder 6)
  - Charles Ellison and Jordan Lively Receipts 1865 (Folder 7)
  - Charles Ellison and Jordan Lively, Receipts and Deeds 1866-1867 (Folder 8)
  - Charles Ellison and Jordan Lively Receipts 1868-1869 (Folder 9)
  - Charles Ellison and Jordan Lively, Receipts and Certificates 1870 (Folder 10)
  - Charles Ellison and Jordan Lively Receipts 1871-1874 (Folder 11)
  - Charles Ellison Lists and Receipts 1875 (Folder 12)
  - Charles Ellison and Jordan Lively Lists 1876-1878 (Folder 13)
  - Charles Ellison Lists and Receipts 1879 (Folder 14)
  - Charles Ellison Lists and Jordan Lively Estate 1880-1881 (Folder 15)
  - Summonses 1883 (Folder 16)
  - Lists and Agreements 1887-1888 (Folder 17)
  - Receipts, Lists, Accounts, Deed, Petition and Certificate 1889-1892 (Folder 18)
  - Orders, Receipt, Reports, Survey, Tailor and Grade 1893-1897 (Folder 19)
  - Lumber Price List, Railway Schedule and Cancelled Checks 1898-1899 (Folder 20)
  - Teaching Certificate, Agreement, List and Cancelled Checks 1901 (Folder 21)
  - Menu, Receipts, Ledgers, Payment Note, Cancelled Checks 1902-1903 (Folder 22)
  - Bill of Lading, Shipping Order and Cancelled Checks 1904 (Folder 23)
  - Cancelled Checks 1905 (Folder 24)
  - Cancelled Checks 1906 (Folder 25)
  - Deeds, Receipts and Cancelled Checks 1907 (Folder 26)
  - Teaching, Deed, Deposits and Cancelled Checks 1908 (Folder 27)
  - Receipts and Cancelled Checks 1909 (Folder 28)
  - Teaching, Church, Deposits, Receipts and Cancelled Checks 1910 (Folder 29)
  - Receipts 1911 (Folder 30)
  - Receipts 1911-1915 (Folder 31)
  - Deposits and Receipts 1924 (Folder 32)
  - Deposits and Receipts 1925 (Folder 33)
  - Deposits, Receipts and Cancelled Checks 1927 (Folder 34)
  - Deposits and Receipts 1927 (Folder 35)
  - Deposits, Receipts and Cancelled Checks 1928 (Folder 36-37)
  - Ledger Book 1854-1872 (Folder 38)
  - Note, William Hinton 1859 (Folder 39)
  - Notebook, C.L. Ellison 1861 (Folder 40)
  - Note 1861 (Folder 41)
  - Notebook 1862-1865 (Folder 42)
  - Notes and poem, C.L. Ellison 1866 (Folder 43)
  - School Papers 1869 (Folder 44)
  - Notebook 1870 (Folder 45)
- Manuscripts, 1871-1931 and Publications, 1838-1940 (Box 2)
  - Ledger Book 1871 (Folder 1)
  - School Papers 1871 (Folder 2)
  - School Papers, Notebook 1873 (Folder 3)
  - School Papers 1874 (Folder 4)
  - School Papers, Notebooks 1875-1887 (Folder 5)
  - Notebook 1889 (Folder 6)
  - School Papers, Notebook 1893-1894 (Folder 7)
  - Notebooks 1895-1896 (Folder 8)
  - School Papers 1896 (Folder 9)
  - School Papers, "Beirne Ellison Manuscripts 1897 (Folder 10)
  - Notebooks 1898 (Folder 11)
  - School Papers 1899 (Folder 12)
  - School Papers, Notebook 1900 (Folder 13)
  - "To Hymen's Altar" 1912 (Folder 14)
  - "Roll of Young People" 1931 (Folder 15)
  - Advertising 1838 (Folder 16)
  - Grammar 1859 (Folder 17)
  - News Clippings 1867 (Folder 18)
  - Atlas 1874 (Folder 19)
  - Orthography Textbook 1875 (Folder 20)
  - "Star List of Grapes" 1878-1881 (Folder 21)
  - Incomplete booklet, Advertising 1883 (Folder 22)
  - Small incomplete booklet, brochure, clippings 1887 (Folder 23)
  - Commencement Program 1893 (Folder 24)
  - Mountain Lake Brochure, Advertising 1895-1896 (Folder 25)
  - Catalogs, Brochures, Advertising, Booklets, Map 1897 (Folder 26)
  - Catalogs, Brochures, Advertising, Booklet 1898 (Folder 27)
  - Catalogs, Brochures, Advertising, Booklet 1899 (Folder 28)
  - Mountain Lake Hotel Prospectus, Brochures, Advertising, Booklets 1900 (Folder 29)
  - Political flyer, Brochure 1901 (Folder 30)
  - Miniature Almanac, Political Flyer, Advertising 1902-1903 (Folder 31)
  - Nursery Price List, Booket, Maps 1904-1909 (Folder 32)
  - Cookbook, Advertising, Brochures 1911-1915 (Folder 33)
  - Photograph of Duxbury Bay, Massachusetts 1926 (Folder 34)
  - Church Bulletin 1932 (Folder 35)
  - Church Bulletin 1933 (Folder 36)
  - Church Bulletin 1934 (Folder 37)
  - Church Bulletin 1935 (Folder 38)
  - Church Bulletin 1936 (Folder 39)
  - Church Bulletin 1937 (Folder 40)
  - Church Bulletin 1938 (Folder 41)
  - Church Bulletin 1940 (Folder 42)
- Charles, Leona and Beirne Ellison Correspondence (Box 3)
  - Charles Ellison 1865-1876 (Folder 1)
  - Charles Ellison 1877-1883 (Folder 2)
  - Leona Ellison 1871-1880 (Folder 3)
  - Leona Ellison 1881 (Folder 4)
  - Leona Ellison 1882 (Folder 5)
  - Leona Ellison 1883 (Folder 6)
  - Leona Ellison 1884 (Folder 7)
  - Leona Ellison 1885 (Folder 8)
  - Leona Ellison 1886-1887 (Folder 9)
  - Leona Ellison 1888 (Folder 10)
  - Leona Ellison 1889 (Folder 11)
  - Leona Ellison 1890 (Folder 12)
  - Leona Ellison 1891 (Folder 13)
  - Leona Ellison 1892 (Folder 14)
  - Leona Ellison 1893 (Folder 15)
  - Beirne Ellison 1885-1893 (Folder 16)
  - Beirne Ellison 1894 (Folder 17-18)
  - Beirne Ellison 1895-1896 (Folder 19)
  - Beirne Ellison 1897-1898 (Folder 20)
  - Beirne Ellison 1898 (Folder 21-23)
  - Beirne Ellison 1898-1899 (Folder 24)
  - Beirne Ellison 1899 (Folder 25-29)
  - Beirne Ellison 1899-1900 (Folder 30)
- Beirne Ellison Personal and Business Correspondence (Box 4)
  - Beirne Ellison, personal 1900 (Folder 1-7)
  - Beirne Ellison, personal 1901 (Folder 8-12)
  - Beirne Ellison, personal 1902 (Folder 13-17)
  - Beirne Ellison, personal 1903 (Folder 18-32)
  - Beirne Ellison, personal 1904 (Folder 33-34)
- Beirne Ellison Personal and Business Correspondence (Box 5)
  - Beirne Ellison, personal 1908 (Folder 1-4)
  - Beirne Ellison, personal 1909 (Folder 5)
  - Beirne Ellison, personal 1910 (Folder 6)
  - Beirne Ellison, personal 1911 (Folder 7-8)
  - Beirne Ellison, personal 1912 (Folder 9-10)
  - Beirne Ellison, personal 1920-1938 (Folder 11)
  - Beirne Ellison, business 1889-1890 (Folder 12)
  - Beirne Ellison, business 1892 (Folder 13)
  - Beirne Ellison, business 1894-1895 (Folder 14)
  - Beirne Ellison, business 1897 (Folder 15)
  - Beirne Ellison, business 1898 (Folder 16-17)
  - Beirne Ellison, business 1899 (Folder 18-21)
  - Beirne Ellison, business 1900 (Folder 22-24)
  - Beirne Ellison, business 1901 (Folder 25)
  - Beirne Ellison, business 1902 (Folder 26)
  - Beirne Ellison, business 1903 (Folder 27-28)
  - Beirne Ellison, business 1904 (Folder 29)
  - Beirne Ellison, business 1909 (Folder 30)
  - Beirne Ellison, business 1910 (Folder 31)
  - Beirne Ellison, business 1911 (Folder 32)
- Beirne Ellison Business Correspondence, Grace Ellison Correspondence, Nannie Ellison Correspondence (Box 6)
  - Beirne Ellison, business 1912 (Folder 1-5)
  - Beirne Ellison, business 1926-1933 (Folder 6)
  - Beirne Ellison, business 1934-1936 (Folder 7)
  - Grace Ellison 1899 (Folder 8-11)
  - Gracie Ellison 1900 (Folder 12-15)
  - Gracie Ellison 1901 (Folder 16-17)
  - Nannie Ellison 1889 (Folder 19)
  - Nannie Ellison 1890 (Folder 20-22)
  - Nannie Ellison 1891 (Folder 23)
  - Nannie Ellison 1892 (Folder 24)
  - Nannie Ellison 1893 (Folder 25-26)
  - Nannie Ellison 1894-1895 (Folder 27)
  - Nannie Ellison 1898 (Folder 28-29)
  - Nannie Ellison 1899 (Folder 30)
  - Nannie Ellison 1908-1909 (Folder 31)
  - Nannie Ellison 1910 (Folder 32-35)
  - Nannie Ellison 1911 (Folder 36-42)
- Nannie Ellison Correspondence, Miscellaneous Correspondence (Box 7)
  - Nannie Ellison 1912 (Folder 1-3)
  - Nannie Ellison 1917 (Folder 4)
  - Nannie Ellison 1919-1926 (Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1864-1885 (Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1890-1891 (Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1892-1894 (Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1895-1898 (Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1899 (Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1900-1902 (Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1903 (Folder 12-13)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1908-1911 (Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1912 (Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1933-1935 (Folder 16)